okay yeah so when
when you are speaking
there's thoughts and then there's this
domain speech that you haven't broken
out into you haven't stolen speaking so
that seems different what's different or
the domain of speech the Devonian
thought okay
but if speech and thought are
fundamentally different than that would
mean that when you're speaking mm-hmm
there's also thinking yeah of course
that the speech isn't in your place in
place of the thought of this but how
about when you're not speaking but
thinking to speak but you're not
actually uttering any sounds is there a
problem with that
as in is there still some sort of
assumption assumption that you can enter
the body with the mind you can you know
like right maybe your body yeah yeah you
can sort of enter the world of the mind
pretty much like a linear almost yeah
channeling of your off your thought into
your speech yeah so you're basically
assuming that you can take up hmm the
body take up the body with your thought
with thoughts actually kind of answer
yeah you just sort of any any any any
form of identifying it to whatever
extent to that extent it's a problem
because it's a contradiction in terms
but say you're not speaking you're not
saying anything's you're practicing
silence you're not actually saying
anything your mind of this is always
thinking that so mine does as thoughts
so they're taking up of the mouth of the
verbal domain is that done solely
through speaking oh you can do that even
body being silent yeah that's the thing
so there's different kinds of thinking
this sort of
thinking like verbal thinking thinking
where you're kind of thinking in words
okay so can you think in words without
taking up him up it seems to me no and
because those thoughts are what they are
because of that the way the math works
right so so you can then you can start
to see the difference between your
thinking your thinking gets taking up
the mouth how'd you then not take up the
month
okay let me ask you like this can you
take Adam on huh well
fundamentally now that you take up the
mouth by assuming that you can take up
the mouth yeah so then how do you not
take enough by understanding that he
can't think of a new yeah by not losing
the context of this body of the mouth
untaken both likeable yeah literally
completely beyond my anything I could
possibly think about so there is no and
this is true for Petula and for another
hand there is no speaking without taking
up the mouth mm-hmm we could thought in
the same sense there is no grabbing
things with your hand without taking up
your hand with your mind but surely so
that that would be the same like there's
no walking across the room without
taking up your body without the body
becoming so you do sort of take the body
mentally as the way across the room yeah
but surely an hour how could do without
taking up the body no no well see that's
why I'm trying to point out here taking
up does not mean assume here taking up
literally means followed it
intentionally give you verbal intended
mental intention so determining taking
up means determining it you can sort of
use can we save a lot Peaks our use no
the volley which is already after you've
taken up taking up is it intending upon
it yeah
so you intend upon the body basically to
that extent you took it up that's where
you can walk sit move whatever is the
new limbs same its speaking yeah
but speaking it's as you said before
it's a more particular way of taking up
the body sure but it's a verbal taking
up the volume in the same words for the
mind mental attention basically taking
up of the mind of that which is the
thoughts the ideas that have presented
himself said that seems to be a Clemson
link between the body and the mind and
speech bit yes but I would say that it's
the same principle if they sound even
when walk when you move across the room
you you're you're doing it because you
want to do it it's a
attention well by the way the reason why
seems to be a closer link is because
you've been practicing physical
restraint for a number of years now yeah
well so you're taking up the body as a
written out of habit yeah has been sort
of suppressed a long time ago what is
the widow would say that behavior has
been purified well beforehand yeah
but yes now it's time to do that with
the mouth yeah and then eventually
you'll be able to do that on the level
of the mind and then yes there is no
problem in any domain because that's
where everything was routed but the
point is to recognize that taking up of
the mouth is how you speak you cannot
speak how without taking every month so
how can you what you want to learn
discern is taking up the mouth but
without assuming the identity of the
verb of the main and mental domain yeah
so what I'm saying is you want to
recognize that taking up does not
automatically mean assumption so how do
you recognize that it's what's the first
thing you have to do you know stop
speaking restrain your speech stop speaking a
restrain your speech stop speaking a
sense of don't engage in an unwholesome
speech yeah executive which then extends
to the point of speaking without a
purpose it's unwholesome for the development of
it's unwholesome for the development of
the mind some palapa that's one of the
aspects of rock speech speaking nonsense
speaking yeah exactly true limit so you
didn't speak when needed
because again speaking is not a problem
but the problem is that you can't
differentiate it from assuming the
identity of the verbal and mental domain
emerging same different whatever being
confused about it so taking up of speech
means taking up of the body fluid taking
up of everything bodily which means then
you're subjected to everything bodied to
the hindrances namely you take up the
whole body by taking the dispiace
so that's why and if your practice
Janna's the then we said like
mindfulness or not speaking basically
mindfulness of the mouth that hasn't
taking up ease with mindfulness to the
bodies at the time for you yeah yeah
this is just more more specific type of
a mindfulness to the body like being
there discerning the extent of the
bodily domain yeah and that's how you
undermine your own sense of ownership of
it you realize there is no before or
after this or above or below I am within
it and I cannot step outside and the
extent of it it's doesn't matter how far
it goes how near it comes can ever enter
me as in my mind and my thoughts can
never enter it it's always these two
simultaneous things present there
together yeah so in order to let's say
you know to understand what your honor
is is it well having
having Jonah manifested as I say yeah
which is basically the imperturbable
image of the correct extent of that body
yeah and that's the sense of safety that
comes from it judo is anything anything
any disturbance is within this extent
did now I see fully in its nature so it
begins by you know you said before it
begins by understanding the extent of
the sensual domain and by overcoming
making yourself safe from containment
this which involves mindfulness of the
body
and then and so understanding the body
to the extent dance this is what is the
absolute end of safety from the nuances
something you're responsible for
yeah not acting out sure
but more more specifically more
accurately than that like what is the
necessary basis for you acting out by
body or best Beach dietary shift the
body taking it up yeah no no no semi
yeah its ownership of course but you
don't need to think in terms of
ownership you just think it up cuz you
can yeah so if you don't have to not
take it up while it's there and during
on its own means there is no basis for
hindrance you're basically pertain to you join to
you're basically pertain to you join to
you yeah so the practice of John and
then his practice of not taking up yeah
but then first of all you might say you
begin by not taking up the body then
then the body becomes this more
particular aspects of the body
sure speech yeah but just while you were
still at it you see you begin that's
true we have to be careful because in
the beginning you not taking up the body
is what you take up yes so you need to
start thinking about the ways of not
taking up the body yeah but it takes
time until you start discerning body on
its own terms
yeah which then maybe this can't be like
an exact clear has not been taking up
but if you're not clear about it and
it's certainly if you're anything out of
your craving you will be ok I'm not
taking away I'm not taking up which is
your very extreme way of taking it up so
taking up is kind of a matter of your
choice not taking up isn't not taking up
is basically removing the basis for
taking up the dead results in the
experience of not taking it up so the
removing for basis of taking up the body
is cela keeping Cilla removes the basis
of taking up the body then you can get
to understand how to not take it up in
that negative sense same with speaking
that i said like it's you're mindful of
the fact that the mouth is not speaking
there is no voice being uttered sound
being there is no communication or
expression which means now if there is any taking
which means now if there is any taking
up its not being perpetuated by the
actual act on the verbal domain but
they're only in the attitude of your
mind and that's where you can see it but
you can't see it in the level on the
level of your mind as an attitude of
taking up while you're talking in the
same sense you can't see on the level of
your mind attitude sensuality while
you're engaging in sexuality impossible
so taking up simply means determining
like yeah and and basically what it
means means thinking about it in a way
see the only way you take up your mouth
is literally by having a thought of
taking it up yeah there's a lot of them
it's like way that's hidden from you
that the ways you take up your mouth for
as long as there's a possibility to take
out the mouth you've taken it up yes and
as I said that's not the problem you
thinking about the mouth as in I'm about
to speak or I want to say something else
on the problem the problem is the
significance of that thought of taking
of your mark you haven't understood it
so for you that thought carries the
assumption because the the possibility
of take the mouth is because I can
mentally like I can speak and I seem to
say things and who do seem to hear them
so my speech is real my voice is real me
taking up or the mouth is real thus I am
taking it up because I can and that's
never the problem the problem is that
that also means you're assuming the
ownership of it so how can you take it
up without owning it how can you take it
up without confusing the two domains how
can take it up without identifying your
thought with your speech or
interchanging or whatever else I
understand exactly but the practicing
restraint in regard to it and then by
understanding the extent of that not
speaking mouth while it's being taken
off mentally then you actually get to
stop taking me mentally because you
realized that thought of the mouth
cannot take us out in that material
sense that is being assumed yeah so it's
only a direction of the mind towards
speech but you can only break into
speech from it
non verbal domain not from the domain of
your thought that's a heavy-laden ponder
one break one breaks into speech see me
the
the determinations for speech are not
mental double you say that verbal
physicists as a particular as these
three domains no I mean I mean their
mental determination for speech speech
is verbal determination for speeches on
verbal it's a determination for verbal
so the termination for speech is
basically the thought of the mouth that
thinks I'm demanding upon them
yeah but not specifically you think
about the look of the mouth now what a
mind comes down into this cavity so yeah
in the same sense you want to grab
something basically your mind is in your hand yes
basically your mind is in your hand yes
so basically yeah you've got you're
basically thinking about something but
that has a shape that has some kind of
bodily shape it does it's assumed on
some extent of the body and see that's
already how you get to like how did the
so does it like embody as we spoke the
other day embody your personality view
into the body as if that's possible so
when you stop assuming that your mind
it's in your hand when it's about to
take something you want yeah is actually
in your hand but then you myself so my
mind is not in my hand but that's
another fun relationship between mind
there is no relationship there is no
mind there is the hand and the sense of
space that's revealed basically by the
body but its secondary already to that
mind so when you want to speak can you
speak without placing your mind again so
to speak in your mouth you can't that is
the necessary condition for speech yeah
the next city determination and that's a
thought and whatever you're about to say
it's within that thought as further of
your of those thoughts yeah but in the
jhana you don't have that taking up of
the mouth anymore you have thinking and
pondering but that embodying of those thoughts
but that embodying of those thoughts
into the verbal cavity that's not there
and that's why speech has subsided its
ceased during that time because at that
time you're unable to take up the mouth
and that's how you that's the difference
between somebody who is in the first job
somebody who is simply not speaking
anything verbally in his mind through
all of those verbal words and thoughts
that you said every of those like images
and concepts that are already organized
every verbalization is habitually taking
up the mantle oh they are not speaking
and that's good because then you can get
to discern it nevertheless that's still
not like that your determination for
speech is ceased yeah but when those
thoughts stop taking up after of the
verbal comedy of the mouth because you
know that well because that's another
thought yeah - it was your thoughts
taking up your thoughts but for you some
of those thoughts stood for the mouth
for the body so then yeah all you have
is thinking and bothering so but that's
that's the funny thing the strange thing
that we are we are skilled at
manipulating the body we've somehow
learned to speak to - to basically we've
got this domain of thoughts from this
domain of speech - completely
incompatible ending being a physical action yeah
well because then it's compatible
incompatible it is a form of
relationship yeah relating them in
components they're invisible to each
other yeah but that's that if they're
invisible to each other it seems it's
remarkable how we have learned how to
it's how to have the speech remarkable
if you come from your point of view but
your point of view is not first so it's
remarkable because the connection
between these things escapes you and it
escapes you because it's actually
fundamentally external to you yes and
that's inconceivable to it
it's just try this yeah make the only
sense you the only reason you have a
sense of self and I am and
logic and the mind is because these
things are there before yeah the body
the verbal domain elemental domain
basically but in order to if like if if
you were to be able to understand how I
was thinking and wondering how has a God
on the bottom is the speech for example
they were required to step outside of
yourself you see how yourself works yeah
and that can only be conceived by
somebody with fully misconceived a sense
of self yeah as something that comes
first it's something that can even think
these theoretical things to be to be
addressed how in a sense of how is
actually second that you already to that
that's the Buddha would he call sorry by
the invalid questions yes no new value
because I don't answer yeah it's based
on the premise yeah let's say when we
learn skills we learn how to speak with
an L to ride a bike or something
oh we doing all we do is just kind of
fumble yeah in some things not knowing
like I said up it's like almost like
this almost like my questions and then
so it doesn't matter series attention
the extent of your learning yeah as a
matter yeah if it's great if it's small
what matters basically is the sense of
assumed ownership in regard to it yeah
which is the truth is to begin with but
yes some people invest more in it some
people less yeah so I practically
speaking physically strength of your
senses celibacy and so on and not
breaking the precepts
he's a necessary basis to outline the
main of taking up the body through
erection then the verbal restraint of
avoiding careless speech malicious page
gossip pointless speech so you're being
silent not because of some you know
great channeling of some energy or
something it's simply because you're
outlining the domain of taking up the
mouth yeah the body the boss which is
again a way of taking of the body
exactly yeah and then eventually you can
also do that on the level of the mind
whereby your own thoughts and images
already taking up
I the body to that extent but it's too
subtle to talk about it now confuse
people so through the physical restraint
you outlined the domain of the body that
you doubt now you're not engaging
because the only way to engage with the
body man is to take it up strong also
the only way to engage with them in a
speech is to take it up through
wholesome that's what precepts need to
come first so practically speaking in
terms of jhana practice jhana
development physical restraint need to
have been done beforehand but now you
start paying attention to a verbal so
when you speak you only speak when there
is a purpose to say something to the
extent that that purpose is expressed
and that's it which means then prevents
any engagement of taking up the body
Candice carelessly through your mouth
yeah and the more you practice that the
less and less you assume that ownership
of the body through your mouth through
saying through communicating and so on
and the less the less you assuming the
clearer it becomes it's its own nature
that it's it's an assumable it's
unknowable and and so and that's
basically the practice of jonah so avoid
unnecessary speech and then use that
silence basically to discern like even
the extent of the physical demands it's
not speaking because that's what your
body is at the time that's where your
mind is and then practice not taking
that up and how you take it up you take
up by thinking beyond it carelessly
failing to see that whatever you're
about to say it's gonna be within the
mouth that's been taken up not after not
before not as a result of its within so
take a mouth taken up is a container of
your whole verbal domain so now you
don't take up the mouth means you have
not taken up or you cannot take up
anything the entire verb of the way
which for you at the time is the bodily
domain that's the sense of safety that
comes in the
the first jhana or are the first down is
the result of that sense of safety
safety from sexuality and everything and
wholesome because physical and verbal as
in your mouth is very physical thing
it's basically what what your body is
for you
presently speaking what I referred to
that even your thoughts a way of taking
up the form that's much subtler and
that's that they would not pertain to
the same coarseness of the body in terms
of sensuality in your will but yeah if
you stick with the development of the
same principle you would arrive at it
but that's like later on when the noble
disciple frees himself from conceit and
all these other subtle self the things
that are not anymore
sort of expressed through the balling
so when you are not speaking you
practice in silence as a practice of
jhana you have thoughts of speaking you
don't try to deny them or remove them
you just now have thoughts of speaking
present enduring and try to not take up
the mouth through them so let them speak
without you taking up the mouth oh can
you say like including them within yes
yeah not speaking letting them be
basically is another way of including
including them within the silence that
you are doing for which you responsible
and you cannot accidentally break
silence you can only choose to be
careless and then break the silence in
the same sense if you practice
mindfulness of the body the Portage's
you cannot accidentally just find
yourself standing you've decided to
stand up so when you practicing silence
as I said you only do so to create a
container within which you want to
include and allow things to be even if
it's a verbal shouting mind doesn't
matter what it is you know that doesn't
matter how loud it gets you are the one
who chooses to speak as a result of it
and you're not doing that so it doesn't
matter how how much your mindfulness
recollection is lapses it'll never lapse
for as long as you don't start speaking
it will never completely lapse and the
more you practice that then the more
familiar you become with what's being
included within it so the verbal thing
it any did those things get to get to
calm down so even your verbal thoughts
will come down because they're not being
expressed and then through that you get
to recognize again by not taking up the
mouth even on the level of your thought
not just through an act of speech but
even on the level of the thought while
that cries them down even more but you
cannot directly talk to your thoughts be
quiet because you just shot at it but if
you can think be quiet
without you taking up the mouth with
that thought that will quiet down the
thoughts
well last one yeah
you can think big quiet okay I said it
now yeah if you just think you don't say
it and then you can just think it
without even taking up the math with
that thought saying thinking be quiet
see be quiet for example here thought of
big word mind because spits it's an
intention yes did you direct it towards
yourself yeah did you then expressed
through that thought yeah so the
direction of quiet expressed to a
thought yeah you took up the mouth and
you said it yeah so you don't say it
yeah first you have the thought that is
taking up the mouth it's saying to
yourself mentally to being wired but
then you can then refine that even
further and then just have a thought of
the direction of quiet without even
taking up the mouth to say because you
don't need to yeah see taking up the
mouth and expressing it is all secondary
to the direction that the thought wanted
to express which was already a form of
expression yes you can so it was only
like a further particular ization of
expression there was already within your
thought but you are used to the level of
taking up the mouth orally saying it or
if big person is very unrestrained doing
it physically what are we saying how the
difference between verbal thoughts and
thoughts that aren't yeah which is the
difference between mental intention and
verbal intention yeah so verbal
intention is the mental intention that
also takes up the mouth first John
avildsen it's verbal taking up has
subsided yeah so you get all the
directions all the expressions without
verbalizing it certainly we are speaking
but also we're not taking up the mouth
which is a basis for speech so then yeah
all you need to do is think be quiet not
in words but in the direction of
significance of being quiet which is
container for saying be quiet yes which
is a container for actually speak
speaking yeah which is a concern for some sort of
yeah which is a concern for some sort of
physical writing it down inside having a
sign shouting at others if they're not
quiet blame or whatever getting upset
trying to distract yourself to
sensuality cuz you didn't get the way
you wanted it to be and so on so you're
silent externally so you get to hear
your thoughts and hearing them you stop
basically verbalize you stop taking up
the mouth through them not by denying
them we're trying to remove them that's
the point here but by including them
because they can be without mouth taken
up but mouth taken up cannot be without
thoughts yeah but for as long as you're
carelessly speaking habitually taking up
the mouth that's what's first for you
then all the thoughts are secondary
basic to it but they're not they're
actually container of it so it always
comes down to correcting establishing
that I ordered
[Music]
and essentially it's starting with the
body has the container of course
yeah the principle doesn't change